Guide to the F. S. Joelson Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
F. S. Joelson papers
1917-1982
GEN MSS 634
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5
(19 boxes)
The collection consists of material relating to F. S. Joelson and his work as editor of the weekly newspaper, East Africa and Rhodesia, and as author of works on East Africa and colonialism. Material includes typescripts of works by or believed to be by Joelson; correspondence and printed material relating to the publication of Joelson's book Germany's Claim to the Colonies (1939); scrapbooks of clippings from the "Who's Who" column of East Africa; scrapbooks of clippings from other East African newspapers; and front page clippings of East Africa and East Africa and Rhodesia. Also included are originals and reproductions of caricatures and cartoons by Ralph Sallon and others. The collection provides insight into British perspectives on Africa during the colonial period of the early- and mid-twentieth century, and documents - in the form of caricature - many of the key figures of the British colony in East Africa prior to the Second World War.
Joelson, F. S. (Ferdinand Stephen), 1893-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Maggs Brothers Ltd. on the Philip and Margaret Neufeld Fund of the Yale Library Associates, 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
F. S. (Ferdinand Stephen) Joelson (1893-1979)
F. S. Joelson was a writer on African affairs and the founder and editor of the weekly newspaper East Africa and Rhodesia, which ran from 1924 to 1967 and was known as East Africa from 1924 to 1938. His published books include: The Tanganyika Territory (formerly German East Africa): Characteristics and Potentialities (1920), Eastern Africa Today and Tomorrow (1934), and Germany's Claims to the Colonies (1939).
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of material relating to F. S. Joelson and his work as editor of the weekly newspaper, East Africa and Rhodesia, and as author of works on East Africa and colonialism. Material includes typescripts of works by or believed to be by Joelson; correspondence and printed material relating to the publication of Joelson's book Germany's Claim to the Colonies (1939); scrapbooks of clippings from the "Who's Who" column of East Africa; scrapbooks of clippings from other East African newspapers; and front page clippings of East Africa and East Africa and Rhodesia. Also included are originals and reproductions of caricatures and cartoons by Ralph Sallon and others. The collection provides insight into British perspectives on Africa during the colonial period of the early- and mid-twentieth century, and documents - in the form of caricature - many of the key figures of the British colony in East Africa prior to the Second World War.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into five series: I. Writing Files, 1939, undated. II. Other Papers, 1917-1982. III. Scrapbooks, 1930-1972. IV. East Africa and Rhodesia Clippings, 1925-1964. V. Caricatures, 1930-1938.
East Africa and Rhodesia; East Africa; Authors, English -- 20th Century; British newspapers -- 20th Century; Newspaper editors -- England -- 20th Century; Africa, East -- History; Germany -- Colonies -- Africa; Great Britain -- Colonies -- Africa; Caricatures; Cartoons (humorous images); Clippings (information artifacts); Scrapbooks; Joelson, F. S. (Ferdinand Stephen), 1893-; Sallon, Ralph, 1899-
- Writing Files, 1939, undated; Series I; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by title of work.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains typescripts of works about East Africa, including essays and articles by Joelson, some which are signed "Effendi," two unpublished books believed to be by Joelson, and correspondence and reviews of Joelson's book, Germany's Claim to the Colonies (1939).
  - Blockade Runners, proof, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - East African Intelligence Department, typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - An Escape from Imprisonment in East Africa: A True Tale of the War, typescript and sketch map, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Germany's Claim to the Colonies
    - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Reviews, clippings, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Reviews, typescripts, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Punishing the Native, typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Sketches from the Tanganyika Territory, typescript, undated
    Arranged into files by chapter.
    - Dar-es-Salaam (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Its Origin and Development (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - The Native Town (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - To the Interior by the Central Railway (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - A Safari (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Along the Rufiji (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - The Benefits of Civilization (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Education, Missions, and Work (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Islam in East Africa (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - The Negro Family (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Some Native Characteristics (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - The Carrier (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Personal Boys (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - The Shauri (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Bado (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Woman in Savage Africa, typescript, undated
    - Foreword (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - The Daily Life of the Village (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - The Ngoma (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Native Marriage (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Polygamy (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - The Birth Rate (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Europeans and Their Native Concubines (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Europeans Who Degrade Their Fellows (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - A Tribute to the Women of the Outposts (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Other Papers, 1917-1982; Series II; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Arranged largely by format.
  - Account book, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - East Africa and Rhodesia
    - E. A. R. Leaders, caricatures, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Correspondence regarding sale of original caricatures, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Promotional cards, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Clippings, 1942-1963 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - "The Black Slaves of Prussia: An Open Letter Addressed to General Smuts" by Frank Weston, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Clipping about Jan Christian Smuts, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Maps of East Africa, 1917-1970 (Box 2, Folder 39-42)
  - Printed material relating to East Africa, 1970-1982 (Box 2, Folder 43-44)
  - Printed material relating to East Africa, 1970-1982 (Box 3, Folder 45-48)
- Scrapbooks, 1930-1972; Series III; 2.58; (9 boxes)
  Arranged into two subseries: East Africa and Thematic and Other.
  - East Africa
    These scrapbooks contain clippings of the "Who's Who" column of the East Africa weekly newspaper dating from 1930 to 1939 and featuring caricatures by Ralph Sallon. Four of the scrapbooks contain manuscript indexes of subjects.
    Related Archival Materials note
    Series V. includes other documentation of Sallon's carticatures.
    - I. Caricatures Nos. 1-69, 1930-1931 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - II. Caricatures Nos. 70-159, 1931-1933 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - III. Caricatures Nos. 160-274, 1933-1934 (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - IV. Caricatures Nos. 275-413, 1935-1938 (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - V. Caricatures, 1938-1939 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Thematic and Other
    These scrapbooks contain clippings of articles by particular journalists or on particular topics concerning East Africa, especially Kenya, which were featured in various East African newspapers, including the Kenya Weekly News.
    - 1945-1947 1945-1947 (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - Kenya Political, 1946-1963 (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - J. F. Liscombe, 1947-1950 (Box 6, Folder 56)
    - Lt. Col. C. H. Stockley and Miscellaneous, 1947-1949, undated (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - East Africa Miscellaneous, 1949-1950 (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - Lt. Col. C. H. Stockley and General, 1950-1951, undated (Box 7, Folder 59)
    - National Parks, circa 1950-1965 (Box 8, Folder 60)
    - Historical, 1962-1965 (Box 8, Folder 61)
    - Game Parks, 1962-1966 (Box 8, Folder 62)
    - Safari, 1962-1969 (Box 9, Folder 63)
    - Leslie Brown, 1963-1967 (Box 9, Folder 64)
    - 1965-1968 1965-1968 (Box 10, Folder 65)
    - Tribal, 1967-1971 (Box 10, Folder 66)
    - Fishing, 1967-1970 (Box 10, Folder 67)
    - Coast, 1967-1973 (Box 11, Folder 68)
    - Game Parks, Lodges, Tourism, 1967-1970 (Box 11, Folder 69)
    - History, 1968-1971 (Box 12, Folder 70)
    - Mountains, 1969 (Box 12, Folder 71)
    - Ecology, 1972 (Box 12, Folder 72)
- East Africa and Rhodesia Clippings, 1925-1964; Series IV; 0.5; (2 boxes)
  This series contains front page clippings of the East Africa and Rhodesia weekly newspaper dating from 1938 to 1964, and of the East Africa weekly newspaper dating from 1925 and 1938.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - East Africa Clippings, 1925, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 73)
  - East Africa and Rhodesia Clippings, 1938-1960 (Box 13, Folder 74-79)
  - East Africa and Rhodesia Clippings, 1961-1964 (Box 14, Folder 80-86)
- Caricatures, 1930-1938; Series V; 0.88; (5 boxes)
  This series contains original caricatures in pen and ink by Ralph Sallon drawn for the East Africa weekly newspaper with handwritten identifications on the verso, as well as two cartoons by Sallon, three pen and ink and watercolor caricatures by Ernest Scott, and one pen and ink cartoon by L. A. Stronach. Also found are reproductions of caricatures by Sallon, which are unidentified and unsorted and some of which duplicate the originals.
  Original caricatures by Sallon are arranged alphabetically by surname of individual depicted. Cartoons and works by other artists and reproductions of caricatures by Sallon are arranged in files at the end.
  - Originals, A-B (Box 15, Folder 87)
    - Abrahams, Sir A.
    - Arthur, Dr.
    - Bailor, Montague [?]
    - Banks, Deaf
    - Barret
    - Belard [?]
    - Black, T. Campbell
    - Bottomley
    - Bourdillon
  - Originals, C-F (Box 15, Folder 88)
    - Calwell, Keith
    - Carter, Sir Morris
    - Chambers, Bishop
    - Clarke, G. H.
    - Dallas, Captain
    - Davis
    - Delamere, Lord
    - D [?]
    - Figgis, E. K.
  - Originals, G (Box 15, Folder 89)
    - Gibbon, Canon
    - Gilks, Dr.
    - Gillan
    - Gillman
    - Goodhind
    - Gowers, Sir William
    - Grundy
    - Guilbride, Capt. F. L.
  - Originals, H (Box 15, Folder 90)
    - Hawkins, Col. E. B. B.
    - Henn, Sir Sydney
    - Hobley
    - Hoey
    - Hollis, Sir Claud
    - Howard, Major
    - Huggings, G. M.
    - Hunter, W. C.
  - Originals, K (Box 16, Folder 91)
    - Kampf, M. D.
    - Kearton, Cherry
    - Kemp, C.
    - Kennedy, Mackenzie
    - Kettles-Roy
    - Kinnear
    - Kitson
  - Originals, L (Box 16, Folder 92)
    - Leakey, L. S. B.
    - Leggett, Sir Humphrey
    - Leonard, Major
    - Lewin
    - Loveridge
  - Originals, M (Box 16, Folder 93)
    - Macintyre, Donald
    - Maffey, Sir John
    - Malcolm, D. O.
    - Masasi, Bishop of
    - Maxwell, Marcuswell
    - May, Bishop
    - McElderry
    - McHardy
    - Miles, A. T.
    - Modera, Col.
  - Originals, N-P (Box 16, Folder 94)
    - Northcote, Sir G. A. S.
    - O'Keeffe, Lanegan [?]
    - Partridge, T. M.
    - Paterson, Col. S.
    - Pearson, Sir Neville
    - Perryman
    - Pim, Sir Alan
    - Playfair
    - Ponsonby, Arthur
    - Popham, Sir Robert Brook
    - Postlethwaite
  - Originals, R (Box 17, Folder 95)
    - Rankine, Sir Richard
    - Rhodes, Sir Godfrey
    - Richardson, Sir Philip
    - Ritchie, Capt. Archibald Thomas Ayres
    - Rittermaster
    - Robbins, Col.
    - Robins, R. E.
    - Russell, L. A.
  - Originals, S (Box 17, Folder 96)
    - Salmon, R. J. D.
    - Scott, Lord Francis
    - Sharpe, Sir Alfred
    - Shorthose, Colonel
    - Smit
    - Stanley, Sir Herbert
    - Storrs, Sir Ronald
    - Swift, Cornelius John
    - Swynnerton
    - Symes, Sir Stewart
  - Originals, W-Y (Box 17, Folder 97)
    - Walsh
    - Watkins, Col. O. F.
    - Wayland, E. J.
    - Williams, P. B.
    - Wilson, Capt. F. O. B.
    - Young, Sir Herbert
    - Young, Sir Mark
  - Original and clipping, Cartoons by Sallon (Box 17, Folder 98)
  - Originals, Caricatures and cartoon by others (Box 17, Folder 99)
  - Reproductions (Box 18, Folder 100-106)
  - Reproductions (Box 19, Folder 107-112)